<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>  <!-- Required for schema validation and schema-aware editing -->
<!-- <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?> --> 
<!-- This third-party XSLT can be enabled for direct transformations in XML processors, including most browsers -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<!-- If further character entities are required then they should be added to the DOCTYPE above.
     Use of an external entity file is not recommended. -->

<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="std"
  docName="draft-kemp-jadn-information-model-00"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates=""
  submissionType="IETF"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">
<!-- 
    * docName should be the name of your draft
    * category should be one of std, bcp, info, exp, historic
    * ipr should be one of trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902, pre5378Trust200902
    * updates can be an RFC number as NNNN
    * obsoletes can be an RFC number as NNNN 
-->

  <front>
    <title>JSON Abstract Data Notation (JADN)</title> <!-- https://authors.ietf.org/en/rfcxml-vocabulary#title-4 -->
    <!--  The abbreviated title is required if the full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-kemp-jadn-information-model-00"/> <!-- https://authors.ietf.org/en/rfcxml-vocabulary#seriesinfo -->
    <!-- Set value to the name of the draft  -->
   
    <author fullname="David Kemp" initials="D." role="editor" surname="Kemp"> <!-- https://authors.ietf.org/en/rfcxml-vocabulary#author -->
    <!-- initials should not include an initial for the surname -->
    <!-- role="editor" is optional -->
    <!-- Can have more than one author -->
      
    <!-- all of the following elements are optional -->
      <organization>Independent</organization> <!-- https://authors.ietf.org/en/rfcxml-vocabulary#organization -->
      <address> <!-- https://authors.ietf.org/en/rfcxml-vocabulary#address -->
        <postal>
          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country></country>
          <!-- Can use two letter country code -->
        </postal>        
        <phone></phone>
        <email>dk190a@gmail.com</email>
        <!-- Can have more than one <email> element -->
        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>
   
    <date year="2026"/> <!-- https://authors.ietf.org/en/rfcxml-vocabulary#date -->
    <!-- On draft submission:
         * If only the current year is specified, the current day and month will be used.
         * If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, the current day will
           be used
         * If the year is not the current one, it is necessary to specify at least a month and day="1" will be used.
    -->

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <!-- "Internet Engineering Task Force" is fine for individual submissions.  If this element is 
          not present, the default is "Network Working Group", which is used by the RFC Editor as 
          a nod to the history of the RFC Series. -->
    
    <keyword>information-model abstract-schema</keyword>
    <!-- Multiple keywords are allowed.  Keywords are incorporated into HTML output files for 
         use by search engines. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document defines an information modeling language designed to improve the rigor
        of Internet technical specifications. Existing data standards like ABNF, XSD, and JSON Schema
        define formal syntax for text and structured data values. But while
        <xref target="RFC3444"/> and <xref target="RFC8477"/>
        establish goals for information modeling, adoption remains limited.
        JSON Abstract Data Notation (JADN) addresses this by defining a formal syntax for
        information using a uniform type structure that balances simplicity with extensibility
        and expressive power.
        The defining feature of any IM is equivalence across data formats, but unlike traditional IM and DM
        schema languages, a JADN schema is itself an information value. This ensures equivalence
        across schema representations, allowing authors to select or design a representation
        suitable for the application and target audience.
      </t>
    </abstract>
 
  </front>

  <middle>
    
    <section anchor="intro">
    <!-- The default attributes for <section> are numbered="true" and toc="default" -->
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t><xref target="RFC3444"/> begins: "There has been ongoing confusion about the differences
        between Information Models and Data Models for defining managed objects in
        network management." The confusion can be partially attributed to the absence of a
        definition of information itself, so this specification begins with two:
      </t>
      <dl newline="true">
        <dt>Information (Information Technology):</dt>
        <dd>structured, processed data that has been given context, meaning, and semantics
          within a specific domain. It turns raw facts into usable knowledge by organizing
          data objects, their attributes, and their relationships, typically at a high level
          of abstraction, independent of physical storage protocols.</dd>
        <dt>Information (Information Theory):</dt>
        <dd>the reduction of uncertainty, measured as the statistical rarity of a message
          rather than its semantic meaning. It quantifies how much a data point reduces doubt,
          measured in bits.</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>
        Given a data value, the information it conveys can be viewed as the questions it answers.
        An information model (IM) defines equivalence between messages in different formats,
        and a concise message such as an RFC 791 IP packet contains the identical information
        (both semantics: "What is the source address?" and its entropy: "32 bits")
        as an equivalent verbose message in JSON or XML format.
      </t>
      <t>
        An implementable IM specification must also define Information Value, Data Value,
        and the relationships between them:
      </t>
      <dl newline="true">
        <dt>Information Value</dt>
        <dd>
          the value of a variable (a typed unit of state) in a processing environment.
          In this specification information values are displayed with strings in single quotes
          to distinguish them from similar-looking JSON data values.
        </dd>
        <dt>Data Value</dt>
        <dd>
          a fixed sequence of bytes usable outside a processing environment.
          Also known as a Document, Message, File, Stream, Literal, or Lexical Value.
          Because messages are immutable they can be compared for equality and
          hashed or signed for integrity.
        </dd>
        <dt>Type</dt>
        <dd>
          definition of the possible content of an information or data value.
          An IM type has three properties: an information value space, a literal space
          for each data format, and a small set of functions and relations including ordering
          of the value space and mappings from each literal space to the value space.
          This definition extends the <xref target="XSD-2">XML Schema</xref> Datatype to
          information modeling by including the literal spaces and mappings for multiple
          data formats. Both information and data values are instances of Type.
        </dd>
        <dt>Object</dt>
        <dd>
          the implementation of a variable in a processing environment.
          An object has a type, a current value, and the behavior defined for variables of that type.
          Objects are instances of Class.
          This is not specific to object-oriented programming languages: K&amp;R C has
          an "int" type, and its implementation of int variables (the int class) has behavior such as
          addition and comparison in addition to the value space defined by the int type.
          Note that <xref target="ECMA-262">JavaScript</xref> defines Boolean, String, Number,
          Array, Map and Set objects, while <xref target="RFC7159">JSON</xref> confusingly uses
          "object" to refer only to the literal values of Map objects. In this specification object
          includes variables of all types as in JavaScript, not just Maps as in JSON.
        </dd>
        <dt>Data Format</dt>
        <dd>
          a named equivalence mapping between information values and literal data values, implemented as
          a set of encoding rules. More than one data format can be defined for the same media type, to
          reflect preferences for conciseness or style.
        </dd>
        <dt>Equivalent</dt>
        <dd>
          Two data values are equivalent if and only if they are the same type and are mapped to
          the same information value.
        </dd>
      </dl>
      <section>
        <name>Objectives</name>
        <t>The objectives of JADN are:</t>
        <ol>
          <li>
            <t>
              The IM must be abstract, unambiguously defining information values at a high level
              that separates information sharing requirements from implementation details.
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>
                Implementation details include programming language and data format.
              </li>
              <li>
                The IM is a high-level definition of structured information that can be used as formal
                pseudocode in documentation and standards even if it is not used to process data.
              </li>
              <li>
                Segregating mapping methods into encoding rules allows the schema to be abstract.
              </li>
              <li>
                The encoding rules that define a data format must be bi-directionally unambiguous
                to ensure that equivalence is verifiable.
              </li>
              <li>
                Readability for the widest possible audience is JADN's highest priority.
                Humans are the primary audience for IMs; DMs are machine-oriented and may be less
                suited to understanding and explaining structured information.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
              An IM schema must itself be an information value, to support representation in
              multiple formats.
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>
                Presenting a schema in a format familiar to the audience aids understanding.
                Schema-specific formats (e.g., property tables, entity relationship diagrams)
                may be more understandable to some audiences than general data formats.
              </li>
              <li>
                An IM schema can also be encoded in a general data format and can either accompany
                or be referenced by the data it defines. <xref target="RFC8949">CBOR</xref> has an
                objective that "Data must be able to be decoded without a schema description".
                This refers to well-formedness but also includes "self-describing", referring to
                validity and tags.
                CBOR data that includes a JADN schema in CBOR format is both self-describing and more
                concise than repeating Item Validity data in every instance.
                A schema in <xref target="RFC8610">CDDL</xref> format is not suitable for
                this purpose because it conflicts with CBOR's compact decoder objective.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
              The IM must unambiguously define equivalence between information values used in most processing
              environments and data values in most data formats used in Internet standards.
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>
                The schema must be composed of data types, not classes or objects, because only types
                define the mapping between external data and internal information values.
              </li>
              <li>
                Associative arrays (maps, dictionaries, hashes) are universally used in programming but
                are not defined as types in UML, ASN.1, or XSD.
              </li>
              <li>
                Other common processing types such as sets, ordered maps and unordered lists must be
                available in the IM for use if needed.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
              The IM language should be both conceptually simple and easily extensible to promote
              integration with existing data modeling approaches.
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>
                Simplicity includes both structural uniformity and composition using the minimum
                set of elements needed to be sufficiently comprehensive. Those elements should be
                mutually exclusive and collectively exhaustive.
              </li>
              <li>
                In addition to its use as pseudocode, an IM serves as a single source of truth
                when generating multiple DMs. Simplicity promotes both uses.
              </li>
              <li>
                An unlimited variety of formally standardized, coalition sponsored, and company
                promoted DM languages are used in the Internet.
                Translation among DM languages is not necessarily lossless, but a structurally uniform
                IM language that covers the entire intersection and much of the union of their
                capabilities simplifies translation to, and reverse engineering from, DMs in
                those languages.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
            The IM language must be usable for modeling data directly, to address data formats where
            DM languages are non-existent or insufficiently capable.
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>
                There is no DM language available to validate <xref target="RFC791">IP Packets</xref>.
              </li>
              <li>
                JSON Schema does not define ordered maps, e.g., document sections indexed by both name
                and position such that front matter must appear before back matter.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
              There is no requirement for information values to be uniquely encoded. However:
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>
                Encoding rules should define a canonical mapping from information to data, to facilitate
                equivalence verification and extend integrity and authentication mechanisms from data
                to the information it represents.
              </li>
              <li>
                Encoding rules should define many-to-one mappings, where helpful, from data to information
                to support the <xref target="RFC1958">Robustness Principle</xref>. Using an IM to validate
                incoming data against well-defined mappings to a schema is
                <xref target="RFC9413">Virtuous Intolerance</xref>.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </section>
      <section anchor="examples">
        <name>Examples</name>
        <t>
          Example representations of a trivial GPS Coordinate type illustrate that a JADN schema
          is an information value, that that value can be represented in multiple data formats,
          and that the information value is identical regardless of format.
          The formats shown are:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>JSON data: the normative storage format for JADN schemas</li>
          <li>XML data: an XML format composed of JADN elements, called XML Abstract Schema Definition (XASD) language.</li>
          <li>Text: JADN Information Definition Language (IDL), an example domain-specific language (DSL).
            Because a JADN schema is an Abstract Syntax Tree (AST), meta programming and projection editing
            tooling is particularly applicable.
          </li>
          <li>Property Tables: a widely-used data standards publication format, shown as Markdown source.
            Tables can also be represented in HTML, XML and office document data formats.</li>
        </ul>
        <figure anchor="intro-jadn">
          <name>JADN Native JSON Format</name>
          <artwork>
          <![CDATA[
{
  "types": [
    ["Coordinate", "Record", [], "GPS Coordinate", [
      [1, "latitude", "Number", ["y-90.0", "z90.0"], "Latitude"],
      [2, "longitude", "Number", ["w-180.0", "z180.0"], "Longitude"]
    ]]
  ]
}
          ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <figure anchor="intro-xasd">
          <name>JADN XASD Format</name>
          <artwork>
          <![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Schema version="2.0">
  <Types>
    <Type name="Coordinate" type="Record">GPS Coordinate
      <Field fid="1" fname="latitude" type="Number" minInclusive="-90.0" maxInclusive="90.0">Latitude</Field>
      <Field fid="2" fname="longitude" type="Number" minExclusive="-180.0" maxInclusive="180.0">Longitude</Field>
    </Type>
  </Types>
</Schema>
          ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <figure anchor="intro-jidl">
          <name>JADN IDL Format</name>
          <artwork>
          <![CDATA[
Coordinate = Record                             // GPS Coordinate
   1 latitude         Number=[-90.0, 90.0]      // Latitude
   2 longitude        Number=(-180.0, 180.0]    // Longitude
          ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <figure anchor="intro-table-md">
          <name>JADN Property Table, Markdown Format</name>
          <artwork>
          <![CDATA[
**Type: Coordinate (Record):** GPS Coordinate

| ID | Name          | Type                   | \# | Description |
|----|---------------|------------------------|----|-------------|
| 1  | **latitude**  | Number=[-90.0, 90.0]   | 1  | Latitude    |
| 2  | **longitude** | Number=(-180.0, 180.0] | 1  | Longitude   |
          ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="requirements">
      <!-- anchor is an optional attribute -->
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
          RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
          interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
          all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
      <!-- The 'Requirements Language' section is optional -->
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="types">
      <name>Types</name>
      <t>
        A JADN schema is composed exclusively of types, not a mixture of types and other mechanisms
        variously called classes or objects in other data modeling approaches. Types are organized
        in schema packages where a <xref target="packages">package</xref> optionally defines metadata shared
        by all types, including a namespace to support cross-package type references using qualified names.
      </t>
      <t>
        The top-level structure of a JADN package is:
      </t>
      <sourcecode>
        <![CDATA[
["Schema", "Record", [], "Definition of a JADN package", [
  [1, "meta", "Metadata", ["[0"], "Information about this package"],
  [2, "types", "ArrayOf", ["*Type"], "Types defined in this package"]
]]
        ]]>
      </sourcecode>
      <t>
        Every JADN Type has the identical five-element structure, which can be verified as being well-formed
        without validating element content:
      </t>
      <ol>
        <li>TypeName: the name of the type being defined.</li>
        <li>CoreType: The JADN built-in type of the type being defined.</li>
        <li>TypeOptions: a set of zero or more TypeOption values applicable to CoreType (conditional).</li>
        <li>TypeDescription: a non-normative comment (optional).</li>
        <li>
          Fields: an array of zero or more <xref target="type-item">Item</xref> or
          <xref target="type-field">Field</xref> definitions as applicable to CoreType (conditional).
        </li>
      </ol>
      <figure anchor="type">
        <name>JADN Type Definition</name>
        <artwork>
        <![CDATA[
[TypeName, CoreType, [TypeOptions], TypeDescription, [Fields]]
        ]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>
        This uniform structure makes a JADN schema capable yet easy to process.
        Currently-defined TypeOptions and FieldOptions provide significant expressive power, and unlimited
        space for new options enables easy extensibility.
      </t>
      <t>
        JADN defines information values and message syntax based on twelve Core types in three categories,
        based on well-known abstract concepts such as "integer", "sequence" and "map".
        These concepts are not exhaustively defined here because many other publications provide excellent
        definitions.
        However, this specification will attempt to describe them well enough that they can be readily
        recognized and distinguished from other abstractions with which they may be confused.
      </t>
      <t>
        The JADN Core types are:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <xref target="primitive">Primitive</xref>: Five types where each instance is an atomic value.
          The Fields array is empty in primitive type definitions.
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref target="collection">Compound</xref>: Five types where each instance is a collection of values.
          The Fields array is empty for unstructured compound types (ArrayOf, MapOf) and has the same
          five-element Field structure for all structured compound types (Array, Map, Record).
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref target="union">Union</xref>: Two types where each instance is selected from a set of possible values.
          Each Field is a three-element Item structure for the Enumerated type, and the five-element
          Field structure for the Choice type.
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        The Item structure for Enumerated types is:
      </t>
      <figure anchor="type-item">
        <name>Item Definition</name>
        <artwork>
        <![CDATA[
[ItemId, ItemValue, ItemDescription]
        ]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>
        The Field structure for Compound and Choice types is:
      </t>
      <figure anchor="type-field">
        <name>Field Definition</name>
        <artwork>
        <![CDATA[
[FieldId, FieldName, FieldType, [FieldOptions], FieldDescription]
        ]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>
        JADN types form a directed acyclic graph (DAG) from top-level root node(s) down to
        leaf nodes that are not further decomposed. Definitions can be arranged in hierarchical
        tiers for readability, and types can be referenced from multiple definitions.
        This differs from tree graphs where types are always acyclic and denormalized,
        and from mesh graphs that make no distinction between contained and referenced content.
        Cross-references (links / foreign keys) in a DAG support cyclic relationships where needed,
        but are the exception rather than the rule.
        Data must live somewhere, and only a model that distinguishes values from references
        specifies where in a document or message to find it.
      </t>
      <section anchor="optionset">
        <name>Options</name>
        <t>
          <xref target="options"/> lists all TypeOptions and FieldOptions defined in this specification.
          Their meaning and usage is described under specific types in the following sections.
          Each option has a numeric ID, a name, and a value type. In JSON format options are serialized
          as a list of strings using <xref target="taggedString" format="title"/> encoding for brevity.
          In tagged strings the Unicode codepoint of the first character is the option ID and the remaining
          characters are the string representation of its value.
          Tagged strings highlight that options are enumerated, not arbitrarily-named attributes.
          Tagged string encoding can also be used for general data by defining mapping tables similar to
          <xref target="options"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          In the GPS Coordinate example, latitude has options represented in JSON format as ["y-90.0", "z90.0"].
          From <xref target="options"/> the first character "y" (U+0079 = ID 121) has name
          "minInclusive", the remaining characters are the value string "-90.0", and the type "BType" is a
          JADN-reserved keyword indicating that the value type is the base type of the field (Number).
          The information value of the latitude options is {'minInclusive': -90.0, 'maxInclusive': 90.0}:
        </t>
        <figure anchor="taggedString">
          <name>Tagged String</name>
          <artwork>
          <![CDATA[
+----+-----------+     Tagged String TypeOption = "y-90.0" (String)
| ID | Value     |     ID = 121 = U+0079 = lower case "y"
+----+-----------+     Info: Name = "minInclusive", Value = -90.0 (Number)
          ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>
          The more verbose XASD representation: &lt;type="Number" minInclusive="-90.0" maxInclusive="90.0"&gt;
          is equivalent to the to the JSON representation because both are mapped to the same information value.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="options">
          <name>TypeOptions and FieldOptions</name>
          <artwork>
          <![CDATA[
  ID TypeOption   Type   ID       Description
 ___ __________  _______ ___ __________________________________________
  61 id          Boolean  =: Fields are indexed by FieldId, not FieldName
  42 valueType   String   *: Value for ArrayOf and MapOf is referenced type
  43 keyType     String   +: Key for MapOf is referenced type
  35 enum        String   #: Enumeration derived from referenced type
  62 path        String   >: Path names derived from referenced type
  37 pattern     String   %: String matches regular expression
 117 default       BType  u: Default value
 118 const         BType  v: Constant value
 119 minExclusive  BType  w: minimum value, excluding bound
 120 maxExclusive  BType  x: maximum value, excluding bound
 121 minInclusive  BType  y: minimum value
 122 maxInclusive  BType  z: maximum value
 123 minLength   Integer  {: minimum string length or collection count
 125 maxLength   Integer  }: maximum string length or collection count
 113 unique      Boolean  q: ArrayOf instance is an OrderedSet
 115 set         Boolean  s: ArrayOf instance is a Set
  98 unordered   Boolean  b: ArrayOf instance is a Bag
 111 ordered     Boolean  o: Map, MapOf, Record instance is an OrderedMap
  67 combine     Integer  C: Choice instance is an untagged union
  47 format      String   /: Semantic validation keyword
  69 scale       Integer  E: Fixed point scale factor, value * 10^n
 116 tagString   String   t: Table for tagged-string serialization
  97 abstract    Boolean  a: Type is not instantiable as a value
 102 final       Boolean  f: Type cannot have subtypes
 101 extends     String   e: Type is a superset of referenced type
 114 restricts   String   r: Type is a subset of referenced type
  65 attr        Boolean  A: Data value may be an XML attribute

  ID FieldOption  Type   ID       Description
 ___ __________  _______ ___ __________________________________________
  91 minOccurs   Integer  [: min cardinality, default = 1
  93 maxOccurs   Integer  ]: max cardinality, default = 1
  48 nillable    Boolean  0: Instance may have no value
  38 tagId       Integer  &: field that specifies tagged union type
  60 dir         Boolean  <: flattened field type may be a collection
  75 key         Boolean  K: field is the primary key for TypeName
  76 link        Boolean  L: field links to an instance of FieldType
          ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <section anchor="fieldOptions">
          <name>FieldOptions</name>
          <t>
            TypeOptions apply to specific types, but FieldOptions apply to the individual fields of
            structured <xref target="compound" format="title"/> types independently of FieldType.
            The FieldOptions are:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>
              minOccurs, maxOccurs: specify the <xref target="s-multiplicity" format="title"/> shortcut.
            </li>
            <li>
              nillable: specifies that the field's information value space includes the <em>null</em> value
              in addition to the values specified by its type. Every <xref target="s-multiplicity" format="title">
              optional</xref> field without a default value is also nillable, but no required field without the
              nillable option may have a <em>null</em> value.
            </li>
            <li>
              tagId:
            </li>
            <li>
              dir:
            </li>
            <li>
              key:
            </li>
            <li>
              link:
            </li>
          </ul>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="primitive">
        <name>Primitive Types</name>
        <t>
          A primitive type has no substructure, and specifies an unrestricted space of atomic values
          without regard to processing mechanisms or data format. Options applicable to each type limit
          the value space; if more than one option is present the value space is their intersection.
        </t>
        <t>
          JADN defines the following primitive types:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li><xref target="boolean">Boolean</xref>: a value from the set of two possible states.</li>
          <li><xref target="integer">Integer</xref>: a value from the discrete whole number line.</li>
          <li><xref target="number">Number</xref>: a value from the continuous real number line.</li>
          <li><xref target="string">String</xref>: a sequence of characters.</li>
          <li><xref target="binary">Binary</xref>: a sequence of octets.</li>
        </ul>
        <section anchor="boolean">
          <name>Boolean</name>
          <t>
            A Boolean instance has one of two values, denoted true and false. Its value space is the set
            of those two values, representing a single bit of information. Its literal space typically
            includes many representations including {true, false}, {1, 0}, or {non-empty, empty} strings
            or collections. Each data format should designate a single canonical information-to-literal
            mapping, and as many literal-to-information mappings as make sense for the application.
            For example, JSON defines the 4-5-character literals true and false but a concise JSON
            data format could specify numeric literals 1 and 0 instead.
          </t>
          <t>
            Options: const, default, format.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="integer">
          <name>Integer</name>
          <t>
            An Integer instance is a value from the ordered countably infinite space of discrete values
            {..., -2, -1, 0, 1, 2, ...}.
          </t>
          <t>
            Options: const, default, format, scale,<br/>
            maxExclusive, maxInclusive, minExclusive, minInclusive.
          </t>
          <t>
            An integer is often said to be a number with no fractional part. Integer and number are
            distinct types, both mathematically and computationally, because a countably infinite set
            of discrete values differs from a continuum.
            1.01 has a fractional part, as does 1.00000000001, as does 1 + 10^-n for every non-infinite
            positive n. For this reason every decimal character string and every IEEE-754 floating point
            value that represents an integer, regardless of precision, also represents an infinite number
            of real values with a fractional part. It is impossible for the number type to uniquely represent
            an integer without consuming infinite resources.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="number">
          <name>Number</name>
          <t>
            A Number instance is a value from the ordered uncountably infinite space of real numbers.
          </t>
          <t>
            Options: const, default, format,<br/>
            maxExclusive, maxInclusive, minExclusive, minInclusive.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="string">
          <name>String</name>
          <t>
            A String instance is a sequence of characters from a character set.
          </t>
          <t>
            Options: const, default, format, pattern,<br/>
            maxExclusive, maxInclusive, minExclusive, minInclusive,<br/>
            minLength, maxLength.
          </t>
          <t>
            Value range options are meaningful only if character set (encoding) or collation order are known.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="binary">
          <name>Binary</name>
          <t>
            A Binary instance is a sequence of octets.
          </t>
          <t>
            Options: const, default, format,<br/>
            maxExclusive, maxInclusive, minExclusive, minInclusive,<br/>
            minLength, maxLength.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="collection">
        <name>Collection Types</name>
        <t>
          An IM collection is a collection of information values and its equivalent
          literal data values. Every collection type has two components:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>
            a <strong>semantic</strong> type that characterizes the properties of an information
            value within a processing environment, based on the <xref target="UML"/> MultiplicityElement.
          </li>
          <li>
            a <strong>compound</strong> type that characterizes the data structure used to represent a
            collection information value.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          These components are equally important, and any IM must specify both
          <xref target="multiplicity">semantics</xref> and
          <xref target="compound">structure</xref>.
          A JADN CoreType is one of five compound types that is combined with a TypeOption to specify
          semantics. But it would also be possible for CoreType to specify one of the six semantic types
          combined with TypeOptions to specify data structure.
        </t>
        <section anchor="multiplicity">
          <name>Collection Semantic Types</name>
          <t>
            <xref target="UML"/> defines MultiplicityElement as specifying collection multiplicity (the valid
            number of values contained in the collection) and four semantic types based on two Boolean properties.
            Because UML does not support mapping types, JADN defines a third Boolean property to enable them:
          </t>
          <dl>
            <dt>isOrdered</dt>
            <dd>
              if true then the collection is ordered. This implies that there is a mapping from positive integers
              to the values in the collection.
              If a collection is not multivalued, then the value for isOrdered has no semantic effect.
              If false then no assumptions can be made about the order of the values.
            </dd>
            <dt>isUnique</dt>
            <dd>
              if true then the collection must be unique. That is, no two values in the collection may be equal.
              If a collection is not multivalued, then the value for isUnique has no semantic effect.
            </dd>
            <dt>isAssociative</dt>
            <dd>
              If true then the collection is associative. This means that there is a mapping from keys to the
              values of the collection, where each key is an immutable value of any type and keys must be unique
              within the collection.
              If false then values are not associated with keys.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>
            Taken together, the isOrdered, isUnique, and isAssociative properties specify that a collection
            value is one of six semantic types. Because keys are unique the combination of isUnique=false
            and isAssociative=true is not used.
          </t>
          <t>
            <xref target="semanticTypes"/> shows the name commonly used for each combination of
            collection properties, and the compound type(s) that can support that semantic type.
            Compound types without options (shown in bold) have either Sequence or Map semantics.
            But it is fairly common for data modelers to use other combinations such as using
            arrays of data values with "id" fields to represent Map semantics.
          </t>
          <table anchor="semanticTypes">
            <name>Semantic and Compound Types</name>
            <thead>
              <tr><th>isOrdered</th><th>isUnique</th><th>isAssociative</th><th>Semantic Type</th><th>Compound Type</th></tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr><td>true</td><td>false</td><td>false</td><td><xref target="sequence" format="title"/></td>
                <td><strong>ArrayOf</strong><br/><strong>Array</strong><br/></td></tr>
              <tr><td>false</td><td>true</td><td>false</td><td><xref target="set" format="title"/></td>
                <td>ArrayOf+set</td></tr>
              <tr><td>true</td><td>true</td><td>false</td><td><xref target="orderedSet" format="title"/></td>
                <td>ArrayOf+unique</td></tr>
              <tr><td>false</td><td>false</td><td>false</td><td><xref target="bag" format="title"/></td>
                <td>ArrayOf+unordered</td></tr>
              <tr><td>false</td><td>true</td><td>true</td><td><xref target="maps" format="title"/></td>
                <td>ArrayOf+key<br/><strong>MapOf</strong><br/><strong>Map</strong><br/><strong>Record</strong></td></tr>
              <tr><td>true</td><td>true</td><td>true</td><td><xref target="orderedMaps" format="title"/></td>
                <td>ArrayOf+key+ordered<br/>MapOf+ktype+ordered<br/>Map+ordered<br/>Record+ordered</td></tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>

          <section anchor="sequence">
            <name>Sequence</name>
            <t>
              A Sequence is an ordered collection of values where a value can appear more than once and each value
              is mapped to a positive integer (its position). Sequences may be combined into a new sequence whose values
              are the concatenation (in order) of each of the sequences (in order). Adding or removing a value
              changes the positions of all following values.
            </t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="set">
            <name>Set</name>
            <t>
              A Set is an unordered collection of values where no value appears more than once and no
              value has a position. Set operations include union, intersection, difference and symmetric difference.
              Coercing a set into a sequence yields a sequence of values in unspecified order.
            </t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="orderedSet">
            <name>OrderedSet</name>
            <t>
              An OrderedSet is an ordered collection of values where no value appears more than once.
              Because values have a position they may be inserted or removed from the collection by either
              position or value.
              OrderedSet values may not be directly combined, but must be coerced into and then combined
              with either Set or Sequence, yielding different results.
            </t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="bag">
            <name>Bag</name>
            <t>
              A Bag (or <xref target="MULTISET" format="title"/>) is an unordered collection
              of values where values may appear more than once. A Bag can be instantiated efficiently as
              a set of unique values with each value mapped to its count.
              Two Bags are equal if they contain the same elements each with the same count.
              A Sequence, Set, OrderedSet or Bag can be combined into a destination Bag by iterating
              over each value in the sources and incrementing the count of that value in the destination.
            </t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="maps">
            <name>Map</name>
            <t>
              A Map is a collection of key:value pairs where the keys are a Set.
              Each key and each value may be any type and keys must be immutable.
              Because Map keys must be unique, a collection of key:value pairs that supports duplicate
              keys may be modeled as a Set of Map values or a Map of Set values.
            </t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="orderedMaps">
            <name>OrderedMap</name>
            <t>
              An OrderedMap is a collection of key:value pairs where the keys are an OrderedSet.
              Each key and each value may be any type and keys must be immutable. Some
              programming languages define "order-preserving" mapping types. These are ordered only
              if two collections with the same elements in a different order compare as unequal.
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section anchor="compound">
          <name>Compound Types</name>
          <t>
            A JADN compound type specifies the data value used to represent collection information.
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>
              Structured compound types <xref target="array" format="title"/>, <xref target="map" format="title"/> and
              <xref target="record" format="title"/> define the type of each element individually, by position,
              key, or both. Each <xref target="type-field">Field</xref> defines the association between the
              identifier (position and/or key) and the field type.
            </li>
            <li>
              Unstructured compound types <xref target="arrayOf" format="title"/> and
              <xref target="mapOf" format="title"/> have uniform field types rather than individually-defined fields.
              ArrayOf is a generic collection structure that can represent any semantic type.
            </li>
            <li>
              The <em>minLength</em> and <em>maxLength</em> options specify the
              minimum and maximum number of elements in any collection information value. Element
              <xref target="primitive">defaults</xref> may affect the length of data
              values that represent the collection.
            </li>
          </ul>
          <section anchor="array">
            <name>Array</name>
            <t>
              The Array type defines a collection of individually-typed elements where each element has
              a position, commonly referred to as a <em>struct</em>:
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>FieldId is the position of each element, numbered sequentially starting at 1.</li>
              <li>FieldName is a comment that describes the element but does not exist in the collection value.</li>
              <li>
                The information value is a <xref target="sequence" format="title"/> of elements, each with a
                position and type.
              </li>
            </ul>
            <t>
              Applications may refer to Array fields directly by position or define a mnemonic label to refer to
              each field. Because field names do not exist in Array values, applications may use FieldName or
              choose arbitrary position mnemonics without affecting interoperability.
            </t>
            <t>Options: minLength, maxLength, format.</t>
            <ul>
              <li>
                The <xref target="semanticFormats">format</xref> option is a semantic validation
                keyword that defines the valid information values of the struct and its
                representation as a data value.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </section>
          <section anchor="map">
            <name>Map</name>
            <t>
              The Map type defines a collection of individually-typed elements where each element has a key:
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>FieldId is the numeric key of each element, arbitrary but unique within the collection.</li>
              <li>
                FieldName is the string key of each element, following the <xref target="packages" format="title">
                $FieldName</xref> naming convention and unique within the collection.
              </li>
              <li>
                By default the information value is a <xref target="maps" format="title"/> of elements,
                each with a key and type.
              </li>
            </ul>
            <t>
              Options: minLength, maxLength, id, ordered, tagString.
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>
                The <em>id</em> option specifies that elements are identified only by FieldId and that FieldName
                does not exist in element values but may be used as a mnemonic label for FieldId.
              </li>
              <li>
                The <em>ordered</em> option specifies that the information value is an
                <xref target="orderedMaps" format="title"/> of elements ordered by FieldId.
              </li>
              <li>
                The <em>tagString</em> option references a translation table similar to <xref target="options"/>
                that defines a collection of IDs, Names and Types that a data format can use to represent a Map
                information value as a list of <xref target="optionset">tagged strings</xref>.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </section>
          <section anchor="record">
            <name>Record</name>
            <t>
              The Record type defines a collection of individually-typed elements where each element has
              both a position and a key:
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>FieldId is the position of each element, numbered sequentially starting at 1.</li>
              <li>
                FieldName is the string key of each element, following the <xref target="packages">
                $FieldName</xref> naming convention and unique within the collection.
              </li>
              <li>
                By default the information value is a <xref target="maps" format="title"/> of elements,
                each with a position, key, and type.
              </li>
            </ul>
            <t>
              Options: minLength, maxLength, ordered.
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>
                The <em>ordered</em> option specifies that the information value is an
                <xref target="orderedMaps" format="title"/> of elements.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </section>
          <section anchor="arrayOf">
            <name>ArrayOf</name>
            <t>
              The ArrayOf type defines a collection of elements of the same type.
              The required <em>valueType</em> option specifies the type of all collection elements.
              The semantic type depends on both collection options and the type specified by valueType.
            </t>
            <t>
              Options: valueType (required),<br/>
              minLength, maxLength,<br/>
              unique, set, unordered,<br/>
              ordered.
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>
                If valueType is an Array, Map or Record type with no
                <xref target="fieldOptions">key</xref> field,
                ArrayOf specifies a <xref target="sequence" format="title"/> of table rows, with
                the columns defined by valueType fields and the rows indexed by position.
                No collection semantic options are valid.
              </li>
              <li>
                If valueType is an Array, Map or Record type with a
                <xref target="fieldOptions">key</xref> field, by default the information value
                is a <xref target="maps" format="title"/> of table rows, with
                columns defined by valueType fields and the rows indexed by both key and position.
                The <em>ordered</em> option specifies that the information value is an
                <xref target="orderedMaps" format="title"/> of of table rows where order is significant.
              </li>
              <li>
                For all other valueTypes the information value is a
                <xref target="sequence" format="title"/> of values by default.
                A <em>unique</em>, <em>set</em>, or <em>unordered</em> option
                specifies that the information value is an
                <xref target="orderedSet" format="title"/>,
                <xref target="set" format="title"/>, or
                <xref target="bag" format="title"/> respectively.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </section>
          <section anchor="mapOf">
            <name>MapOf</name>
            <t>
              The MapOf type defines a collection of <xref target="maps" format="title"/> elements
              with the same key and value types.
              The required <em>keyType</em> option specifies the type of all element keys.
              The required <em>valueType</em> option specifies the type of all element values.
            </t>
            <t>
              Options: keyType (required), valueType (required),<br/>
              minLength, maxLength, ordered.
            </t>
            <ul>
              <li>
                The <em>ordered</em> option specifies that the information value is an
                <xref target="orderedMaps" format="title"/> of elements. This requires that keyType has
                a defined ordering, unlike the structured <xref target="map" format="title"/> type where
                FieldId ensures that field order is always defined.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="union">
        <name>Union Types</name>
        <t>
          A union type specifies a set of alternatives used to classify a value.
          Like Compound types, Enumerated and Tagged Union types have fields individually identified by tag,
          where the tag consists of an integer FieldID and a string ItemValue or FieldName, each of which
          is local to and unique within the type definition.
          Union types define a set of tags, types or both.
        </t>
        <table>
          <thead><tr><th>Type</th><th>Tag</th><th>Type</th><th>Definition</th></tr></thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr><td>Enumerated</td><td>Yes</td><td>-</td><td>Vocabulary, a set of tags</td></tr>
            <tr><td>Choice</td><td>Yes</td><td>Yes</td><td>Tagged union, a set of tag:type pairs</td></tr>
            <tr><td>Choice(combine)</td><td>-</td><td>Yes</td><td>Untagged union, a logical combination of types</td></tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <section anchor="enumerated">
          <name>Enumerated</name>
          <t>
            An Enumerated type defines an explicitly listed set of values, a vocabulary. It is formally
            a degenerate tagged union of unit type because it defines the tags of a tagged union
            with no additional information. In a full tagged union, the tag identifies the type of the
            following data. In an enum, the tag is the data.
          </t>
          <t>Options: id.</t>
          <t>
            JADN tags include both numeric ID and equivalent string value, allowing either to be used.
            The <em>id</em> option specifies that an Enumerated information value is an item_id, otherwise
            it is an item_value that may be represented by the id depending on data format.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="taggedUnion">
          <name>Choice - tagged</name>
          <t>
            The Choice type without a <em>combine</em> option is a tagged union. Its value is a tag
            that selects a type from the specified set of fields and an instance of the selected type.
          </t>
          <t>Options: id.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="untaggedUnion">
          <name>Choice(combine) - untagged</name>
          <t>
            The Choice type with a <em>combine</em> option is an untagged union. Its value is an
            instanced of a logical combination of field types specified by that option:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>1 (allOf): value must be an instance of all field types.</li>
            <li>2 (anyOf): value must be an instance of any field type, tried in field order until a match is found.</li>
            <li>3 (oneOf): value must be an instance of one field type and no others.</li>
            <li>4 (diff): value must be an instance of the first field type and no others.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>Options: combine.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="typeRequirements">
        <name>Type Requirements</name>
        <t>...</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="packages">
      <name>Packages</name>
      <t>
        A package organizes IM types into a group

        ... meaning types within a package must have unique names ...

        and supports modularization by breaking down large models into manageable subunits,
        including libraries of sharable types.
      </t>
      <t>
        JADN packaging is based on XML namespaces:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>A namespace is identified by a Uniform Resource Identifier (URI),
          which is a unique name, not necessarily a link to a network resource.</li>
        <li>...</li>
      </ul>
      <section anchor="pkgMetadata">
        <name>Metadata</name>
      </section>
      <section anchor="pkgRequirements">
        <name>Package Requirements</name>
        <t>...</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="shortcuts">
      <name>Shortcuts</name>
      <t>
        JADN defines a set of core definitions plus several shortcuts that make IM schemas more
        adaptable or less redundant. Shortcuts are syntactic sugar implemented using options that
        can be replaced with additional types without affecting functionality.
        Expanding shortcuts into core definitions simplifies serialization and validation code,
        and viewing the expanded/simplified schema may aid understanding of the IM.
      </t>
      <t>
        The shortcuts and the options used to implement them are:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li><xref target="s-anonymous" format="title"/>: any TypeOption present in FieldOptions</li>
        <li><xref target="s-multiplicity" format="title"/>: minOccurs, maxOccurs</li>
        <li><xref target="s-enumeration" format="title"/>: enum, path</li>
        <li><xref target="s-inheritance" format="title"/>: extends, restricts, abstract, final</li>
      </ul>
      <section anchor="s-anonymous">
        <name>Anonymous Types</name>
        <t>
          This shortcut allows fields within a structured type to be defined without a TypeName.
          Expanding the definition generates an explicitly path-named type for each anonymous field,
          moves all TypeOptions included in FieldOptions to the generated type, and replaces
          FieldType with the TypeName of the generated type.
          FieldType must be a non-structured CoreType, and any TypeOption included in FieldOptions
          must apply to FieldType.
        </t>
        <t>
          Example: a structured type with anonymous fields:
        </t>
        <sourcecode>
        <![CDATA[
Coordinate = Record                   // A GPS coordinate
  1 latitude   Number=[-90.0, 90.0]   // lat: -90 to 90 degrees
  2 longitude  Number=(-180.0, 180.0] // long: -179.9999 to 180 degrees
        ]]>
        </sourcecode>
        <t>
          Expanding the type generates two named types and replaces FieldType with their names.
          This requires a naming convention for generating path names as discussed in
          <xref target="packages" format="title"/>. Path components may be either field IDs
          ("Coordinate.1") or field names ("Coordinate.latitude").
          Writing an IM using explicitly named types (e.g., "Latitude") avoids this shortcut.
        </t>
        <sourcecode>
        <![CDATA[
Coordinate = Record                   // A GPS coordinate
  1 latitude   Coordinate.latitude    // lat: -90 to 90 degrees
  2 longitude  Coordinate.longitude   // long: -179.9999 to 180 degrees

Coordinate.latitude = Number=[-90.0, 90.0]
Coordinate.longitude = Number=(-180.0, 180.0]
        ]]>
        </sourcecode>
      </section>
      <section anchor="s-multiplicity">
        <name>Multiplicity</name>
        <t>
          Fields may be defined to have multiple values of the same type using the minOccurs and
          maxOccurs FieldOptions. This supports multiplicity notation (1..*), which is universally
          used in diagram formats.
          Expanding this shortcut converts each field that can have more than one value to a separate
          path-named ArrayOf type, but leaves single-valued fields (maxOccurs=1 by default) unchanged.
          The default minOccurs=1 indicates a required field, while specifying minOccurs=0 indicates
          that the field is optional.
        </t>
        <t>
          If an optional field instance with no elements should be represented by an empty list rather
          than omitted entirely, the IM collection type uses an explicitly-named ArrayOf type
          in a required field.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="s-enumeration">
        <name>Derived Enumerations</name>
        <t>
          The <em>enum</em> and <em>path</em> options generate a list of items based on the fields
          of the type named in the option. When expanded, enum copies the field id and name directly
          from the named type, while path generates a recursive list of pathnames below the named type.
          The <em>dir</em> field option terminates recursion when expanding the <em>path</em> option
          and when flattening data values from tree to list structures.
          Expanding replaces the shortcut Enumerated type with the explicit item list.
          These options avoid duplicating long field lists, saving space and eliminating potential
          inconsistency.
        </t>
        <t>
          Using the GPS Coordinate example, an Enumerated type with the enum option expands to the
          same type with an explicit list of fields:
        </t>
        <sourcecode>
        <![CDATA[
Foo = Enumerated(Enum[Coordinate])

Foo = Enumerated
  1 latitude
  2 longitude
        ]]>
        </sourcecode>
        <t>
          In the Coordinate type the path option yields the same result as enum because both fields
          are leaf types (Number). But if "latitude" were a hypothetical compound type with additional
          structure, the "path" result would be a list of pathnames:
        </t>
        <sourcecode>
        <![CDATA[
FakeCoordinate = Record    // A GPS coordinate
  1 latitude   Stuff       // lat: a hypothetical structure
  2 longitude  Longitude   // long: -179.9999 to 180 degrees

Stuff = Record
  1 bar/       MoreStuff   // "dir" option stops path recursion
  2 baz        MoreStuff   // otherwise continue to leaf values

MoreStuff = Record
  1 qux        Integer     // a leaf type
  2 xyzzy      String      // another leaf type

Longitude = Number=(-180.0, 180.0]  // also a leaf type

==== Expanding the _path_ shortcut yields: =====

Foo = Enumerated(Path[FakeCoordinate])

Foo = Enumerated
  1 latitude.bar
  2 latitude.baz.qux
  3 latitude.baz.xyzzy
  4 longitude
        ]]>
        </sourcecode>
      </section>
      <section anchor="s-inheritance">
        <name>Type Inheritance</name>
        <t>
          Class inheritance is complex and dynamic because it addresses behavior. But because types define
          immutable value spaces, type inheritance consists of two basic set operations (union and
          intersection) that can be precomputed on a schema rather than being processed at runtime.
          The <em>extends</em> and <em>restricts</em> shortcuts perform these schema operations,
          saving space and improving robustness:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>
            extends: value space is a superset of the base type. If A extends B, A = A ∪ B
            (union), and every instance of B is also an instance of A.
          </li>
          <li>
            restricts: value space is a subset of the base type. If A restricts B, A = A ∩ B
            (intersection), and every instance of A is also an instance of B.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          Two other options are adopted from class inheritance for completeness:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>abstract: type cannot be instantiated as a value.</li>
          <li>final: type cannot be extended or restricted.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          Although the subset rule authoritatively defines inheritance for all types, it
          is not useful for primitive types because:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>a primitive value space is the universe of possible values and cannot be further extended</li>
          <li>existing TypeOptions directly restrict primitive value spaces without designating a base type</li>
          <li>
            the identical result can always be expressed using Choice to "extend" or "restrict" value spaces
            without designating a base type:
          </li>
        </ul>
        <sourcecode>
        <![CDATA[
Name1 = Choice(anyOf)   // extend: 2915, a34c, D72F are valid. g16H isn't.
   1  String{pattern="^[a-z0-9]$"}   // a::
   2  String{pattern="^[A-Z0-9]$"}   // b::

Name2 = Choice(allOf)   // restrict: 2915 is valid. a34c, D72F, g16H aren't.
   1  String{pattern="^[a-z0-9]$"}   // a::
   2  String{pattern="^[A-Z0-9]$"}   // b::
        ]]>
        </sourcecode>
        <t>
          In practice inheritance is used to add or remove fields in structured compound types
          or modify multiplicity in any compound type.
          Because Array and Record fields are indexed by position, extending appends new
          fields at the end. Record field names must be unique, but Array field names are comments
          with no uniqueness requirement.
          Map fields are indexed by key, so extending Map types requires that both field id and name
          be unique, but position has no meaning or effect.
        </t>
        <t>Examples:</t>
        <sourcecode>
        <![CDATA[
Entity = Record abstract            // Base type, cannot be instantiated
  1 id      Integer
  2 name    String optional

Person = Record extends(Entity)     // Add email address
  1 email   String /email optional  // Person type has 1 id, 2 name, 3 email

AnonymousPerson = Record restricts(Person)  // Prohibit name
  2 name    String [0]
        ]]>
        </sourcecode>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="serialization">
      <name>Serialization and Data Formats</name>
      <section anchor="serialization-schema">
        <name>Schema Serialization</name>
        <t>...non-normative examples...</t>
        <section anchor="idl">
          <name>JADN IDL</name>
          <t>...</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="xasd">
          <name>JADN XASD</name>
          <t>...</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="ptable">
          <name>Property Tables</name>
          <t>...</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="erd">
          <name>Entity Relationship Diagrams</name>
          <t>...</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="serialization-data">
        <name>Data Serialization</name>
        <t>
          A JADN IM is based on several equivalence mechanisms that can be included
          in any data format. This enables a single IM to ... CBOR goals ...
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>Indexing Record elements by position or name</li>
          <li>Enumerating data elements by numeric ID or string name / value</li>
          <li>Defining string formats for non-string types</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          ...
        </t>
        <section anchor="json">
          <name>JSON Serialization</name>
          <t>...</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="xml">
          <name>XML Serialization</name>
          <t>...</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="cbor">
          <name>CBOR Serialization</name>
          <t>...</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="packed">
          <name>Packed Serialization</name>
          <t>...</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="semanticFormats">
        <name>Semantic Format Keywords</name>
        <t>...</t>
        <section anchor="jadnFormats">
          <name>JADN Formats</name>
          <t>...</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="xsdFormats">
          <name>XSD Formats</name>
          <t>...</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="jschemaFormats">
          <name>JSON Schema Formats</name>
          <t>...</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA">
    <!-- All drafts are required to have an IANA considerations section. See RFC 8126 for a guide.-->
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="Security">
      <!-- All drafts are required to have a security considerations section. See RFC 3552 for a guide. -->
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document should not affect the security of the Internet.</t>
    </section>
    
    <!-- NOTE: The Acknowledgements and Contributors sections are at the end of this template -->
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7159.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8949.xml"/>
        <!-- The recommended and simplest way to include a well known reference -->
        <reference anchor="XSD-2" target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema11-2">
          <front>
            <title>XML Schema Definition Language (XSD) 1.1 Part 2: Datatypes</title>
            <author>
              <organization>W3C</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2012" month="4"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="UML" target="https://www.omg.org/spec/UML/2.5.1/PDF">
          <front>
            <title>Unified Modeling Language, Version 2.5.1</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Object Management Group</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2017" month="12"></date>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
 
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.791.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1958.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3444.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8477.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8610.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9413.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="ECMA-262" target="https://tc39.es/ecma262/">
          <front>
            <title>Standard ECMA-262: ECMAScript Language Specification</title>
            <author>
              <organization>ECMA International</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2026" month="March"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="MULTISET" target="https://mathworld.wolfram.com/Multiset.html">
          <front>
            <title>Multiset</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Wolfram</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>

      </references>
    </references>
    
    <section>
      <name>Appendix 1</name>
      <t>This becomes an Appendix</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <!-- an Acknowledgements section is optional -->
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>This template uses extracts from templates written by Pekka Savola, Elwyn Davies and 
        Henrik Levkowetz.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Contributors" numbered="false">
      <!-- a Contributors section is optional -->
      <name>Contributors</name>
      <t>Thanks to all the contributors.</t>
      <contact fullname="Jane Doe" initials="J" surname="Doe"><!-- https://authors.ietf.org/en/rfcxml-vocabulary#contact-->
        <!-- including contact information for contributors is optional -->
        <organization>Acme</organization>
        <address>
          <email>jdoe@example.com</email>
        </address>
      </contact>
    </section>
    
 </back>
</rfc>
